<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="css/rss.css" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

<channel>
<title>Roxana's Blog RSS Feed</title>
<description>The RSS feed for my blog.</description>
<language>en-us</language>
<link>rss.xml</link>
<atom:link href="rlazoc.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />

<!-- LB -->

<item>
<title>Installing and using VMware ESXi</title>
<guid>rlazoc.github.io/blog.html#installing-and-using-vmware-esxi</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 22:57:37 CST</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[
			<p>
      In this post, I talk about how to install VMware ESXi and its usages. ESXi
      is an hypervisor provided by VMware to deploy and manage virtual machines.
    </p>
    <p>
      Essentially, it works like Hyper-V (Windows) or KVM (Linux). Here is the
      official description from VMWare's website: <br />
      <i
        >"VMware ESXi formerly known as ESX is a bare metal hypervisor that
        installs easily on to your server and partitions it into multiple
        virtual machines."</i
      >
      <br />
    </p>
    <p>
      I think learning virtualization tools such as ESXi is necessary to get
      used to the technology that may be used in an enterprise setting. I will
      go over what is and its place among the vast options there are in the
      world of hypervisors.
    </p>
    <p>
      Let's go over what is a hypervisor. You can think of a hypervisor as a
      program that lets you create virtual machines. Think VirtualBox or VMWare
      Workstation. But the difference between those hypervisors I stated and
      ESXi is that ESXi is considered a type-1 "bare-metal" hypervisor and the
      software-like ones are type-2 "hosted" hypervisors.
    </p>

    <p>
      These type-1 hypervisors such as ESXi run on the kernel, which is the
      closest thing that communicates with the low-level hardware.
    </p>

    <p>
      The question is why we would need bare-metal hypervisors if hosted ones
      are much simpler to set up and use?
    </p>
    <p>
      There are a number of reasons. But the main ones are that since type-1
      hypervisors are so close to the hardware level, their access is much more
      secure and often faster for production-ready environments.
    </p>
    <p>
      VMWare ESXi is free to download. (As of writing this, the hypervisor is at
      version 7.0). You can visit their
      <a
        target="_blank"
        href="https://customerconnect.vmware.com/en/web/vmware/evalcenter?p=free-esxi7"
        >website</a
      >
      to download it after you have made an account, which is also free.
    </p>
    <p>
      Alternatively, you can use their hosted vSphere labs. But this post is
      going to focus on manually installing and configuring it on our machine.
    </p>
    <p>
      After you have downloaded the ESXi ISO from their website, you need a way
      to boot into it from your machine. I used Workstation but you can create a
      bootable flash drive and load the ISO from it instead.
    </p>
    <p>
      At startup, you will have to wait for all the files to load and install.
      If this went through nicely, you will be greeted with a message to go over
      the setup. These are settings like layout, password, and installing on a
      disk. Once the installation has finished, the server will prompt you for a
      reboot. Restarting the machine displays a similar screen seen in the
      beginning but now a new message shows where you can manage the host and
      use ESXi either through a DHCP or static-assigned IP address. Either one
      works, so load up a browser and type the designated address where you will
      see a login screen. The default username is <code>root</code> and the
      password is the one you made while setting up ESXi. You are now in the
      host. Keep in mind, ESXi in this state is in evaluation mode and expires
      in a limited time. But until then, you are free to explore the hypervisor.
    </p>
    <p>
      I may make future posts going in-depth into parts of the ESXi console, but
      for now have fun looking around the docs once you set it up :)
    </p>
]]></description>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>

